{
  "reference_number": "5266",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "It's important to set a target so we know what we're aiming for, otherwise we risk watering it down."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "Beyond individual circumstances, this is the one of the more urgent issues facing the planet so let's go hard and do it properly."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions (including from new forest planting) and using some emissions reductions from overseas (international carbon units) that have strong environmental safeguards",
      "answer_index": 2,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, but the revision criteria needs to be robust."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - each incoming Government should have the option to review the third budget in the sequence",
      "answer_index": 14,
      "notes": "The budget should not influence the emissions target."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "1. Work closely with local government authorities so that climate action is manageable at a local level. But also please ensure that\n\nlocal councils are mandated to make tough climate-based decisions e.g.: \"we're not going to build that big road because climate\". 2.\nThe way we do transport and agriculture in NZ needs a re-think. 3. The waste industry; the way we import goods and generate waste\n\nneeds a re-think: issues of product stewardship. Food waste. 4. Budget for ongoing communication, engagement and education. I\nsuspect that one of the biggest hurdles will be helping people to understand *why*, so there needs to be a very clear and achievable\ncommunication target. The ultimate goal is that most people understand and agree with the rationale for tough decisions. The\n\ngovernment could impose strict measures to achieve carbon reduction targets, but it will be easier if everyone is on board. That's\nreally hard though, especially when business and convenience are on the line. Everyone is an environmentalist until they want their\n\nown car park. Realistic budget needs to allocated so that, ongoing, the government can engage people with the vision. 5. Whatever\nwe do, it can't be at the expense of people's welfare. Social agencies, iwi and the health sector need to be included in climate\n\nchange mitigation conversations. We have to do the right thing, and the hard thing, but caring for people must remain at the centre.\nWe're trying to save the planet for our children's future after all."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Thinking about the wellbeing of my children and whatever grandchildren may follow, climate change is one of the issues I care about\n\nmost. Yet it's been hard for me to motivate myself to complete this submission. If I'm struggling to engage with something I claim to\nbe passionate about, how much harder will it be for other people to pay attention and make a submission? So, I would like to\n\nacknowledge the difficulty that the government will have in bringing people on the journey through the tough decisions. Please make\nsure you allocate sufficient ongoing budget to help tell the story about what we're doing as a nation, and why. A few years ago I wrote\nsome articles, published in the Bay of Plenty Times, about how we need to do whatever needs to be done to address climate\n\nchange. I've attached them as supporting documentation. They represent my view not as an expert, but as a layperson, a New\nZealander, a human, a citizen of the earth. I recall Bill English saying something like \"I don't think most NZers wake up each morning\nworrying about climate change.\" He's wrong. There are many, many people to whom this matters a great deal because we worry\n\nabout the future that our children and grandchildren will inherit. Thank you for making the first step with this bill."
    }
  ]
}
